Stanford University
All right, so we spoke a little bit
about quantum fields,
uh the quanta of the fields, creation
operators, annihilation operators. We
even went so far as to talk about the
Hamiltonian
operator
for a very simple quantum field
uh satisfying particle satisfying the
Schrödinger equation.
Write it down.
This is what it looked like.
Integral over position.
When I write dx,
you don't need to imagine that it's
one-dimensional. You can imagine that
it's multi-dimensional and x stands for
a collection of coordinates, x, y, and
z.
But I'll write it as if it were
one-dimensional.
And then there's the quantum field psi
dagger. That's the creation operator. It
creates a particle at position x.
And then there's a minus sign. Let's put
the minus sign explicitly over here.
Del squared, the second derivative
operator. And if we put the mass in, the
mass goes downstairs here. That's p
squared over 2m.
That's the standard
kinetic energy of a particle.
And then psi.
If the particle also happens to be in a
potential, if there's a potential
energy,
then you would add in here.
And this of course is also of x.
And then there's a v of x, the potential
times psi dagger of x psi of x.
And the way you would understand this
term
is just every particle, if it's at
position x, has a potential energy v of
x.
Psi dagger of x times psi of x, what is
that? That's the density of particles at
point x.
So, this is just counting the number of
particles at point x and giving each one
an energy a potential energy v of x.
You would write that down classically,
too. You would write down that if you
had a gas of particles
and they were moving in some potential,
you would write that the potential
energy is the integral over all space
the density of particles at point x
times the potential at that point x.
Okay, so
that's the Hamiltonian of a of a system
of particles non-interacting with each
other. They may be interacting with some
potential.
Okay, I'm going to leave out the all.
Tell you what. Um
Yeah.
Let's forget this term for a moment.
No, I'll tell you what. I'm going to put
it back, but I'm going to put it back
v of x and I'm going to take v of x to
be a constant. Now, we all know that a
constant uh
term potential energy doesn't exert any
forces. So, it really doesn't do
anything, but let's put it anyway. A
constant, it doesn't matter what we call
it, times psi dagger of x psi of x.
What kind of term in the energy would
this correspond to?
Well, it's a term which when you
integrate it over x,
it just counts the total number of
particles.
So, if it counts the number of
particles, it's just an energy
proportional to the number of particles.
It's giving each particle an energy. How
much energy does a particle have? I'm
not talking about its kinetic energy.
We've already got its kinetic energy,
but just a particle standing still. Does
a particle standing still have any
energy?
Yeah, it's mc squared.
So, if we wanted to put that in, if you
wanted to keep track of the fact that
every particle has an energy mc squared,
we would put it over here.
But whatever it is, it's a number.
Uh the reason I want to include this
here is for a very simple reason.
I want to spend a minute or two
talking about energy con- uh not energy
conservation, momentum conservation.
How do we see
from
this uh from this expression
that momentum is conserved? Okay, how do
we What does it mean for momentum to be
conserved?
Well,
what does the Hamiltonian do? What's the
role of the Hamiltonian?
The role of the Hamiltonian
is
to
update the state of the system.
If the state of the system at time t
is psi of t. Now, I'm using psi to
indicate a state. I better not do that.
I've already used psi for several
different things. One of them is for the
field operator. One of them is for the
single particle wave functions. I better
not use it again.
So, let's use a different terminology
for the state vector of a system. Let's
not call it psi.
The vector itself, let's call it
phi.
Right, if the if the state of the system
at one instant of time, let's say at
time t,
is the vector psi of phi of excuse
me, phi of t,
then what is it at the next instant of
time displaced
by time epsilon?
Well, the answer is
that's what the Hamiltonian does.
Gives you one
minus
minus i epsilon, that's the little time
interval, little separation of time,
the Hamiltonian
times phi itself.
Sorry, this is phi of t plus epsilon.
The field or the sorry, the state at a
slightly displaced time.
And so what h does is it just updates
things. You can write this
as just phi of t.
That's the same state back again.
Nothing has happened. Plus a little
correction after time epsilon, which is
minus i epsilon.
times the Hamiltonian acting on phi.
That's what the Hamiltonian does.
And you can think of it as being
iterated. You can do it over and over
and over again at each step. That of
course is another way of talking about
the Schrödinger equation. The
Schrödinger equation says the time
derivative of phi is equal to h times
phi.
Uh so that's what the Hamiltonian does.
It changes the state from one instant to
another.
What would it mean
to say that momentum is conserved?
What it means
is that the Hamiltonian, when it acts on
a state of definite momentum, does not
change the momentum.
Whatever the Hamiltonian does,
if it acts on a state of a given
momentum, it must give back a state of
the same momentum if momentum is
conserved.
I'm not saying it is conserved. I'm
saying that's what it would mean.
If the momentum is conserved,
it means that when the Hamiltonian acts,
it doesn't change the momentum of the
system. May change other things, but it
doesn't change the momentum.
Okay, we can check that. This is an
interesting thing to check.
For this Hamiltonian,
does it
change the momentum
of the system?
Okay, let's let's begin by looking at
this term here. Let's forget the other
term and see what it does when it acts
on a state with a total with a given
total momentum.
Okay.
So, what do we want to do? We want to
rewrite this in the momentum basis.
Let me remind you how that worked. That
was just a good old Fourier transform.
Okay, so the way that works
is you say the creation operator for a
Oh, this happens to be the annihilation
operator, but the annihilation operator
for a particle at point x is an integral
over all of the momentum.
The square root of 2 pi, if you want to
keep track of it. In fact, there's a
square root of 2 pi for each direction
of space.
So, if this were three-dimensional,
there would be a 2 pi cubed, but uh
again, this is incidental and not
important.
And then
what we called psi twiddle, I believe,
of p.
This is the annihilation operator for a
particle of momentum p.
This annihilates a particle of momentum
x.
p, but then we have to multiply this by
e
to the i
px
and integrate over p.
That's the creation operator at x in
terms of the creation operator for a
particle of momentum p.
Now, I'm interested in what this
operator does when it acts on a state,
but I'm interested in what it does to
the momentum. So, the natural thing to
do is to rewrite this in terms of the
momentum variables. So, let's do that.
Let's go down here.
mc squared, that's that's
just a number.
And now, we have integral dx.
Now, each one of these can be rewritten
that way.
All right. So, there's an integral.
Let's Let's write Let's write a second
equation here.
psi dagger of x
is a similar integral.
I'm not going to write it as an integral
of p because I've already used p. P is
an integration variable.
I don't want to reuse it. I don't want
to recycle it. I want to use another
variable.
Let's call it q. dq
over 2 pi.
psi dagger twiddle of q
And now, there's an e to the minus i qx.
Why is it e to the minus i qx?
Because we're supposed to put the
complex conjugate wave functions here.
Complex Everything gets complex
conjugated.
Okay, let's take Let's take
psi of x times psi dagger of x, exactly
the thing which appears here.
And then, let's integrate it over x and
see what we get, just for fun. This is
sort of fun, like going to the dentist,
right?
Yeah, okay. So, we multiply the two of
these together
and we get a double integral.
What's that?
This
that?
Yeah, okay.
Okay. So, we get to the dentist
and the dentist, first of all, says 1
over 2 pi.
1 over 2 pi for each direction.
And then, there is
psi twiddle of p
times psi dagger. I suppose we should
put them in the opposite orders and so,
over here, the daggers stand to the
left.
So, let's stand the daggers to the left.
psi twiddle dagger of q
That's this one.
And then,
psi twiddle of p.
We're going to integrate over p and q in
a moment, but let's first put e to the i
p minus q
x.
That's this factor e to the i p minus q.
Question?
No? Okay.
And then, we integrate over x. This
instruction here is to integrate over x.
Okay. Does anybody remember what you get
when you integrate e to the i something
times x over x?
A delta function. Now, the way if you If
you forget that, the way to think about
it is the following.
Supposing p minus q is not zero,
then this is an oscillating thing.
If p minus q is not zero, then it
oscillates with x. What happens if you
integrate something which oscillates as
much positive as negative?
Yeah. Sorry, dp dq.
Okay.
Yeah, it just
depends on the nature of the
oscillation, but if it's all symmetric,
then it That's right. Okay. cancels out.
Well, this is a mnemonic. This is not a
This is not a a rigorous argument. But
if p is not equal to q, it oscillates,
it has a sine in it, a cosine in it. The
sines and cosines are as positive as
they are negative,
and that must integrate to zero.
On the other hand, if p is equal to q,
then this is just one, and the integral
of one over all space is infinite.
So, this is a function of p minus q,
which is zero if p
minus q is not zero. In other words, if
p is not equal to q,
and it's infinite if p equals q.
Obviously, this is proportional to the
Dirac delta function, and with the 2 pi
there, it is the Dirac delta function.
So, this all becomes
We can erase
We can erase the e to the i p minus q.
Erase the integral dx
and just write that this is delta of p
minus q.
And we also get rid of the 1 over 2 pi.
Okay, what happens if we integrate psi
dagger of q times psi of p with a
function which is zero unless p is equal
to q?
Well, it's just the instruction, do the
integral, but set p equal to q. If you
set p equal to q, there's only one
integration, and this is just equal to
psi
dagger twiddle of q.
Let's write it as p.
Instruction here is set q equal to p.
So, this is p.
psi
of p.
Okay. Now, what do we have here?
We have an operator which contains a
destruction operator, an annihilation
operator
times a creation operator.
It's an annihilation operator for a
particle of momentum p. So, if it finds
a particle of momentum p,
it pulls it out and kills it, you know,
it annihilates it. But then, it puts
back a particle of the same momentum.
Notice, here was the important thing.
That by the time you finished,
p had to equal q.
P had to equal q tells you that if you
remove a particle,
you put back a particle of the same same
momentum, and the momentum doesn't
change when this operator operates on a
state, it does not change the momentum.
Whatever it takes out, it puts back.
What was the working ingredient here?
It was the integral over x, which turned
this into a delta function.
Okay. The integral over x turned into a
delta function, and the delta function,
you can say, was the delta function of
momentum conservation.
Momentum that when the Hamiltonian acts,
when it updates the state a little bit,
we somehow
no longer have the little
the updating of the state, but when it
updates the state a little bit, it
doesn't change the momentum. Okay.
Now, we can go
Uh we can do the same thing
with this term here.
Let's do it. Let's go through it, just
to Just just so that you see how the
machinery works. Quick question, please.
What happened to the being infinite when
p is equal to q?
Somehow, we don't talk about it. No, no,
that's okay.
Whenever you integrate a Dirac delta
function
with another function,
you just get that function
at point zero.
That's the definition of the Dirac delta
function.
The fact that it's it's infinite, but of
zero width.
See, it's a thing which is infinitely
high, but infinitely narrow.
The area under it is one unit.
Okay. So, it doesn't give anything
infinite. It just gives back.
And in this case,
it just tells you set p minus q equal to
zero, which is the same thing as setting
p equal to q.
Okay, before I look at this term here,
let me just point out that this could be
more general.
Let's suppose we had a term in the
Hamiltonian which had, for whatever
reason, for reasons that we'll talk
about later,
we had a whole bunch of fields.
They could even be fields for different
kinds of particles.
Creation operator, annihilation operator
for different kinds of particles.
And instead of having just two of them,
we can imagine in the Hamiltonian, and
we'll we'll discuss what this means,
that we could have any number of psi
daggers.
A particle of type A, particle of type
B.
Any number of psis. Particle of type C,
particle of type D. They could all be
the same or not the same.
Uh
any number of psi daggers and any number
of psis.
Suppose in some
insane world,
we put this thing into the Hamiltonian.
What would happen? Well, instead of
getting what we have up
up here, the simple expression, what we
would have is a whole bunch of
integrals.
A p integration for each field that
appears here.
Let's um
Yeah.
Whole bunches of ps.
The ps could stand for the half of the
particles that are being created, for
example. dp1, dp2,
dp3, and so forth. However many
particles
or however many fields there are with
dagger.
And then,
Oh, no, those are qs. Sorry. Qs go with
the daggers.
Ps go with the psis. All right. So, we
have some qs, also. dq1,
however many of those there are.
And then we have a bunch of creation and
annihilation operators of exactly the
same kind
except many of them now.
Side dagger of P1
or side twiddle of P1 dot dot dot.
Side
daggers
sides of Qs
Q1 dot dot dot.
But then the all-important
exponentials.
The all-important exponentials and they
read for each side
Let's see, for each
I think I did it wrong again. QP. If I
wanted to follow the same notation up
there.
P.
Uh, then I would have an e to the i
and then for each P
P1 plus P2 plus P3
all times X.
Each one would come in with its own e to
the i PX and you'd add them all up in
the exponent. But then you'd also have
minus
i
Q1 plus Q2
dot dot dot
X.
In other words, instead of just having a
single P and a single Q
you would have a bunch of Ps
for all the creation operators is it the
which ones get the Ps get the annihil-
Ps go with the annihilation operators
and Qs go with the creation operators.
Okay.
And you have to integrate it over X. You
have to integrate it over X.
What does the integration over X give
you?
Again, it gives you a delta function and
it's a delta function of the sum of all
the Ps minus the sum of all the Qs.
In other words, it's a rule that the sum
of the Ps has to be equal to the sum of
the Qs.
The sum of the Ps
is
all the particles that you take out.
The things with the annihilation
operators. The sum of the Ps is all of
the momentum of the particles that you
put in.
So, it's just a rule. It says the rule
just says
the total momentum of the particles that
you take out must equal the total
momentum of the particles that you put
back.
It's a rule
that
follows from this kind of Hamiltonian
here.
Now, what's really going on is the fact
that this Hamiltonian is translation
invariant, but I wanted to show you how
the machinery works.
And so, whenever you see a Hamiltonian
of this form
that it has a whole bunch of sides and
side daggers
but you integrate it over space. It's
the integral over space which gives you
the delta function. It's the integral
over space which says
momentum conservation momentum
conservation momentum conservation.
It doesn't say that each
that P1 should be equal to Q1 and P2
should equal Q2. It says the sum of all
the incoming momentum should be the same
as the sum of all the outgoing momentum.
Okay, so that's momentum conservation.
In the Hamiltonian, that's the product
of all those field operators. Yeah,
product of all these field operators.
Why would you do that? We'll come to why
you might do that.
Not why you might, why this is the one
of the central um
points of quantum field theory.
But before we do it, let's take this
term in the Hamiltonian over here.
This has the additional derivatives.
Let's go back and ask what would happen
to this calculation
the first uh
the original one here
if we changed it
by
differentiating with minus del squared
the side dagger before we multiply it
with side.
What does minus del squared
This is just a second derivative.
What does it do when it hits here?
Well, to know, we just go over to this
side. Let's differentiate this side
twice with X.
What depends on X? Well, the Q doesn't
depend on X. 2 pi doesn't depend on X.
In fact, side dagger doesn't depend on
X.
The only thing that depends on X are
these oscillating wave functions here.
So, what happens if you differentiate
twice
the oscillation here?
Q squared. Plus Q squared.
Minus iQ times minus iQ. So, this would
give us Q squared.
In other words, the square of the
momentum
of the particle that you're creating
here.
Isn't it minus? No.
That's why.
No, it's minus
Look look at the far left side of the
equation. There's a minus sign. There's
a minus here
and then a minus
I didn't see that one. No.
Right. Thank you.
There's a minus here. That's why this
Well, this minus is here because that's
what goes in the Hamiltonian, but um
yeah.
Okay, so what So, what's the upshot?
The upshot is the same kind of
expression that we had before. Again,
you get to integrate e to the i P minus
QX. It's a going again going to give you
um
uh momentum conservation, but instead of
just having integral side dagger of
side dagger twiddle of P
times side
twiddle of P
that just counted the total number of
particles of each momentum and added
them up.
There's another factor of P squared.
It's this thing here
which when you use the delta function
just gives you P squared.
What is this thing giving you? First of
all, it conserves momentum. The momentum
in and the momentum out have to be the
same for exactly the same reason. But
it's just weighing each particle with
its with the square of its momentum. In
other words, it's counting the kinetic
energy of each particle.
It's just adding up all the particles,
adding up the number operator for each
momentum and multiplying it by P
squared. I suppose where's the 2M? We
left out the 2M.
P squared over 2M.
So, it's doing exactly what it's
supposed to do. It's counting up the
kinetic energy of the particles and
momentum is conserved
because of the uh delta function.
Okay, let me show you an example of an
interesting
term that you could put into the
Hamiltonian. Let's suppose you had
two species of particles.
Let's call one an electron and the other
a proton.
Two species.
Now, I'm cheating because if I really
wanted to do electrons and protons, I
wouldn't be doing boson operators.
Okay, so these are fake electrons and
protons which happen to be bosons.
Let's forget the MC squared term. Uh no,
we're we're not going to worry about the
MC squared term.
What's that?
Um in the conservation of
energy kinetic energy. Yeah, it's only
in the case where
Kinetic energy or
momentum or energy? Kinetic energy.
Kinetic energy, yes.
That's only true in the case where the
potential energy is constant. We haven't
put any Yeah, exactly. Yes, so. That is
so.
That is a true statement. Um what what
what is the interpretation of the side
dagger in the Hamiltonian?
It counts. Side times side dagger is a
counting operator.
In this case, it's counting the number
of particles with each momentum and
multiplying by P squared.
No, no. He He just
He didn't see the multiplication there.
Oh, okay. Good.
Yeah.
You know, there's another trick you can
do.
This thing looks negative, doesn't it?
But of course, everybody knows the
kinetic energy of a particle is
positive.
So, what's going on?
Well
everybody know how to integrate by
parts?
If you have side
dagger of X
and you have two derivatives with a
minus sign d by dx
times d by dx
times side
I'm not going to work this out in
detail. I'm going to tell you the
result.
The d by dx's both act to the right.
They act on side. Integration by parts
allows you to take one of these
derivatives and shift it to the other
side.
In fact, integration by parts would
allow you to take both of them and shift
them to the other side. But I don't want
to shift both of them. I just want to
shift one of them.
But what do you have to do when you
integrate by parts in addition to taking
the derivative and shifting it to the
other factor?
Change the sign. Change the sign. You
also have to worry about edge effects,
but uh but
uh you know, we we won't worry about
that now.
So
you can rewrite this
as
d by dx
of side dagger times d by dx of side.
And now this is just the square of
something and it's positive.
Integrated dx.
That's kind of interesting to see in the
Hamiltonian the square of the derivative
of psi.
It's very much like any other field
theory uh where
what you see in the Hamiltonian is
squares of derivatives of the fields.
Okay, in this case squares the space
derivatives of the fields.
And it's positive. It's positive because
psi derivative of psi dagger times
derivative of psi is positive.
Okay, let's uh
let's take another example of a possible
thing in the Hamiltonian and discuss
what it means.
Now, again, without mathematical proofs
because
uh we're just
uh belabor
points that we've essentially already
made, but uh let's add in here.
Let's assume there are two kinds of
particles first.
I'm not going to give them names. I'm
going to call them A and B. You can call
them proton and electron if you like.
Then first of all, there's the energy of
the electrons. So, this is the field
operator for electrons. It creates and
annihilates electrons. It does nothing
to protons.
This is the kinetic energy of all the
electrons. We have to add to that
the kinetic energy of all the protons.
This is twice M electron. This is twice
M proton.
And then psi
proton of X.
Okay, so far all I have is the um
is the kinetic energies.
Now, I'm going to add something. It's
not the realistic real interaction
between electrons and protons. This is
just a model interaction.
And what I'm going to add is plus the
integral over space integral DX
times
uh
the
creation operator of an electron at
point X
times the creation operator of a proton
at point X
times the annihilation operator of an
electron at point X
times the annihilation of a proton
at the same point X.
Uh and
Yes.
Okay. This comes along and it
annihilates a proton and an electron if
it finds them.
Where does it annihilate them? It
annihilates them at position X. So, if
there happens to be an electron and a
proton, and let's draw this the
following way.
This is a space-time diagram. Here's a
space-time diagram. Here's Here's time.
This is just a way to visualize.
This is not
uh not to be taken too seriously at the
moment.
But, an electron and a proton are moving
around. Here they are.
This is time. This is space.
These are the world lines of the
electrons and the proton the electron
and the proton.
If they're not at the same place
then you can't then this is not going to
give anything if it acts on the state.
This will act on a state and will only
act if it finds both a proton and an
electron at the same place.
It doesn't matter what place because
you're integrating over X, you'll get
some kind of thing no matter where X is
if there are two particles at the same
place.
But, if there are not two particles in
the same place, it just gives zero.
Okay, so first of all it looks for
particles at the same place.
If it finds particles at the same place
it annihilates the proton, it
annihilates the electron
but then it creates a proton
and it creates an electron at the same
point.
It scatters the electron and the proton
is what it does. Electron and proton
come in
and if when they're at the same point
and then they go out
and it scatters them.
Is the momentum conserved? Yes, the
momentum is conserved for exactly the
reason we wrote up there. But, are the
individual momentums conserved? No, the
individual momentums are not conserved.
I should have gone through that here.
The individual momentums are not
conserved. The only conservation of
momentum is the overall conservation.
So, when an operator like this comes
along and hits the state of a
electron-proton system
it scatters the electron-proton system.
So, it's a scattering operator. It's
equivalent to a potential energy between
the electron and proton when they're at
the same spot.
Of course, real electrons and protons
interact even if they're not at the same
spot through the Coulomb potential, but
we're just taking little steps uh one at
a time.
Okay, so um
if through experiment you discovered
that there was an interaction where
electrons and protons
by a short-range potential
short-range meaning it only acts when
they're at the same point scatter each
other
this is what you would put into the
Hamiltonian.
So, it's a kind of experimental uh you
know, a bit of experimental physics to
tell you what kind of uh
things the particles can do.
And once you know what they can do, you
mark it up by
expressions like this. Let's do some
more. Let's uh let's see what else we
could imagine having.
Another thing we can imagine having.
Why is the question what Why is it part
of the Hamiltonian?
Does the energy doesn't
change, right?
That's equivalent to a potential energy
in the Hamiltonian between the electron
and the proton. Oh.
Yeah.
Any other questions?
But, you know
the question um what Hamiltonians do is
change states from one instant to the
next. If you discovered experimentally
that an electron and a proton over a
short period of time will scatter each
other
if they're at the same place
you've got to say there must be
something in the Hamiltonian, the thing
which updates the state which
corresponds to that scattering. And
that's the kind of thing you would write
down.
Okay?
So, when you see in quantum field theory
expressions like this, interactions
involving products of fields
maybe products with different fields,
different kinds of particles, they're
representing these basic simple
interactions where particles, if they're
at the same point can interact with each
other.
Another example, supposing
experimentally you discovered
that particle of type A
could decay
and form particle of type B and particle
of type C. Again, this is time.
Read it from bottom to top.
Particle A comes along
and you discover
that there's a process
where particle A disappears at a point
and particle B and C appear at the same
point.
Okay? You discover in your bubble
chamber uh you discover tracks which
lead you to conclude that A came in, B
and C went out and um
and they came out from the same place
that A came in. What would you write
down?
Well, okay. So,
you need something
to
remove the A. What happens over a short
period of time is an A disappears.
That's an annihilation operator. And a B
and a C are created. So, let's try that.
What kind of thing might we write down?
We might write down the annihilation
operator
for A, for field A
at position X. That's the annihilation
operator.
And then two creation operators, one for
B and one for C.
And you'd say, "Look, I've discovered
experimentally that the state of the
system changes so in such a way that an
A
disappears. That's this. And a B and a C
are produced.
Furthermore, because every point of
space is like every other point of space
you would begin to suspect this could
happen not only at point X, but it can
happen anywhere.
So, you integrate it over X.
Weigh all points of space equally.
Once you do this you can read off
from what we talked about over here
that the momentum is conserved.
The momentum of A becomes the momentum
of B and C. Now, energy conservation is
a little more complicated.
But, um energy is always conserved.
Let's put it that way.
Okay, so um
over the long run anyway.
Okay, so this is uh the
What else would you put into this
Hamiltonian or this term in the
Hamiltonian besides these products of
fields?
How about a number?
For example
in both cases incidentally, I should
have said that also in this case over
here.
There's a possible number, plus
G,
the coupling constant.
The coupling constant is a number which
can be anything.
Uh
and it can uh
be
extremely small if the particles are
very weakly interacting. That would mean
that even if the particles arrive at the
same point, the probability that they
scatter is small.
And you would experimentally verify
this. You would the scatter two
particles and you would discover most of
the time they don't interact. In that
case, G is a small number.
If the particles
have a large interaction
uh probability, then G is a large
number.
And G is called the coupling constant.
Okay, we're on our way to building
quantum field theories.
Let me say one more thing about
this term here.
What goes in the Hamiltonian must be
Hermitian.
That's a rule. Hamiltonians are
Hermitian and that's equal or equivalent
to the statement that the time evolution
is unitary.
Time evolution is unitary because it's
got to conserve probabilities.
Okay, so is this Hermitian?
Well, it's not Hermitian or it's not
Hermitian. And the reason it's not
Hermitian is because the Hermitian
conjugates of a side dagger are a psi.
And the Hermitian conjugates of a psi
are a side dagger.
To make it Hermitian, you must add
its Hermitian conjugate.
Its Hermitian conjugate is the same
operator except with everything replaced
by its conjugate.
And you also have to remember when you
Hermitian conjugate things, you've got
to change the order, but in this case it
wouldn't matter.
But uh let's do it anyway.
It doesn't matter in this case because
if they different fields, they commute
with each other. So let's um but we can
do it. We can do it. Uh psi dagger A of
X
times psi
B of X times psi C of X.
Now, how is this different than this?
The answer is every creation operator
has been replaced by an annihilation
operator, every annihilation operator
has been replaced by a creation
operator.
And the process described by the second
half here, let's look what it says.
It annihilates a C and then annihilates
a B and creates an A.
So it's just the whole thing turned
over. B and C come in
and A go out.
So once you discover that there's a
process where A goes to B and C,
you can immediately conclude that it
must also be the case that if you have a
B and a C, they can
turn into an A.
What's that? Is there any kind of
exception to this?
Is there any exception to this? No.
If there is,
we don't know about it.
Okay, so now we have the basic rules
basic rules of a simple version of
quantum field theory.
You'll have creation and annihilation
operators.
You'll have fields made out of them.
The fields are functions of position and
they can be thought of as creation and
annihilation operators for particles at
definite positions.
Each type of particle has its own field.
And you write down Hamiltonians. The
Hamiltonians always contain or typically
contain
typically contain the kinetic energies
of the particles.
That's the top thing there.
And then in addition, various other
concoctions
which um
let's put it this way. In the uh in the
first round of particle physics, those
concoctions largely came from
experiment.
Well, electrodynamics of course came
from uh a little more than just
experiment. But a classic example is a
theory of beta decay. The theory of beta
decay is a uh neutron decaying into a
proton, an electron, and a neutrino.
Okay?
Proton goes to electron
and so forth.
All right, so what would you write
there? Then you would have four
operators.
This would be
annihilate a neutron,
create a proton,
create an electron,
and create a neutrino.
Let's go one step further.
When I wrote that um
psi
of well,
state vector phi of T plus epsilon
is equal
to phi of T
minus I H bar
minus I epsilon H
times phi of T.
This of course was an approximation. It
was an approximation to leading first
order in small quantities, namely
epsilon.
What would happen if I made epsilon a
little bit bigger?
Well, there would be a next term which
would be order epsilon squared. You know
what it would be?
It would be minus
epsilon squared
over two
times H squared
phi.
This is just another way of saying
that if well, it's a Schrodinger
equation. The Schrodinger equation gives
you the derivative of psi proportional
to H times psi. But it can also give you
the second derivatives of psi and that's
proportional to H squared times psi.
So this is what you would learn if you
went to the next order in small
quantities
that
in the next order in small quantities
there's a change in the state from one
instant to another which is proportional
to H squared times psi.
That's very interesting because for
example,
one of the things it would say, we could
draw we can draw some diagrams now.
What does H squared do? Well, we could
take H squared and multiply it all out.
Okay, we could try to see what it does.
But that's dumb. The easy way to do it
is just to use the the pictures.
We take the pictures.
Let's erase this.
And the picture say that in lowest
order,
a thing which can happen
is B and C can come together and make A.
That's just the Hamiltonian itself or
this term in the Hamiltonian. But
supposing the Hamiltonian acted again on
this.
Well, here's another term in the
Hamiltonian. The same term can act
twice. Oops, this is wrong. B and C.
But this term can't really act twice
because for it to act twice, it has to
find the second time it has to find a B
and a C again.
Well, in the first round here, the B and
the C were eaten.
No B no B and C. So this term can't act
successively twice. But what can happen
is when you square the Hamiltonian, you
can get
this term times this term.
In other words, let's write it out. It's
got the
it's got
psi B
psi C
times psi dagger A
and then
psi dagger A then psi A
psi B
psi C.
A big mess. That's the square of a term
or a piece of the square of the term of
the Hamiltonian.
But it's very easy to see what it says.
It says it takes a B and a C and it
makes an A and the
uh yeah, it takes a B and a C and turns
it into an A and then it takes the A
annihilates the A and puts back a B and
a C.
The effect of this is to contribute or
to create a scattering between B and C.
The A, that's just temporary.
The B and the C came in.
They annihilated to form A and A then
converted back to B and C using the same
Hamiltonian.
So it's not just that the Hamiltonian
updates the state. All the powers of the
Hamiltonian
give you a vast variety of different
processes that can happen
that contribute to the amplitude for
scattering.
This is the amplitude for scattering. B
goes to C.
And the only rule, at least the only
rule we've set up till now, is that
momentum is conserved, total momentum.
The momentum of C can change, the
momentum of B can change, but in going
from beginning to end, the total
momentum should be the same.
Okay.
Should that psi sub C on the left,
should that have a dagger?
Uh possibly, yes.
Right. So, you see, once you learn this
little piece of information,
oh my goodness, all sorts of other
things can happen.
Well, we now know
uh
What did I just do? I erased
A
and B goes to C.
Um
Good.
Here's something else that can happen.
A can come in,
create B and C,
but now, if there happened to have been
another B around, let's suppose there
was another B around to begin with.
Yeah.
This says that if B finds a C
to annihilate with,
then it can make an A.
So, again, in the second order of the
Hamiltonian, where you iterate the
Hamiltonian twice, you not only get
processes in which A goes to B and C,
and B and C go to A, or the B and C go
back to B and C, but now you have a
scattering amplitude where A and B
scatter with each other
with the exchange of a C. This is called
an exchange diagram. It looks as though
you're drawing a picture where a C jumps
over from here to here.
All it is is a contribution to the
scattering coming from the Hamiltonian
twice, acting twice.
So, in following the evolution of the
system, when the Hamiltonian acts twice,
the first time it can take an A and a B
to C, leaving this B over here alone.
This is a different B.
Leaving it alone, not doing anything.
And then the second power of the
Hamiltonian can take C and B and convert
it back to A. So, you see,
once you have
these simple terms in the Hamiltonian,
you have a vast forest of many, many
different kinds of interactions
that are mediated by the same uh by the
same simple term in the Hamiltonian.
That's why quantum field theory is
powerful.
A small number of terms in the
Hamiltonian can lead to a huge number of
different reactions,
all related by having the same form in
the Hamiltonian, the same coupling
constant.
For example, the coupling constant,
yeah.
If there's a coupling constant governing
a term in the Hamiltonian here, then
when you square the Hamiltonian,
you might get the coupling constant
squared.
In fact, you would here.
Each one of these vertices, these are
called vertices, they carry a coupling
constant in the Hamiltonian. So, this
process would have a coupling constant
squared in front of it.
So, this would correlate an enormous
amount of data
about all of the possible interactions
of A's, B's, and C's.
And there many, of course.
This is uh the the most common thing in
the world in particle physics
is to be uh studying those correlations.
Yeah.
So, if if you So, I assume we can have A
uh
this uh decaying into B and C, and then
B and C coming back together, forming A.
But what is that? Sorry. Uh
say it again now. Oh, A going to B and
C, and then B and C coming back
together. That's a self-energy diagram
for an A.
Uh it changes the structure of A. What
it tells you is that a real A particle
that you might measure in the laboratory
spends has a probability to be not just
an A, but to be a B and C close to each
other.
So, what it means is that if you found
an A in your laboratory,
and you scattered something off it, with
some probability, you would find that
that A behaved as if it were a B and a C
together, close together.
So, for example, um
an electron, one uh one such process,
one example of this
would be
an electron emitting a photon.
Electron comes in, electron goes out,
emits a photon.
Okay. So, the operator for that would be
psi dagger electron,
sorry, psi electron that annihilates an
electron,
psi dagger,
create an electron,
and then a photon creation operator.
Photons The photon field is called A.
All at the same point. So, it absorbs an
electron, creates an electron, and emits
a photon.
Okay. So, one of the things that can
happen is Kevin points out, is you can
have the electron moving along, becoming
an electron, emitting a photon, and then
the photon coming back and becoming an
electron. Now, don't take too literally
the statement this happens and then that
happens and then that happens. This is
really just standing for a term second
order in the Hamiltonian, iterating the
Hamiltonian twice. But it's clearly a
very tempting to to um
to try to describe this by saying uh
sequence of things happen. Now, of
course, if you go into the system and
look and see whether that something
happened, you screw up the whole thing,
as usual in quantum mechanics.
So, um but what this does this What this
does tell you is that if you scatter
another electron off the first electron,
you will find some of the time that this
electron contains a photon.
That what you thought was a single
electron really looks like a composite
of an electron with a uh
with a photon.
The probability to find the photon there
is small. It's about 1%, but uh
but that's what it says.
So, it really should be thought of as a
correction to the structure of the
electron rather than a uh than a new
process.
It's uh it only becomes a new process
when you interfere with it and you look
and see what's inside, and some of the
times you will find that what's inside
contains a photon.
Of course, what will happen if you look
for the photon, you'll discover the
photon some of the times, you'll scatter
the photon out, and you'll completely
screw up the the electron. You'll excite
the electron, and uh things will happen.
At that first vertex, are both energy
and momentum conserved? No, only
momentum.
Only momentum.
Right.
And as I said, these things are not
literally happening. They're
shorthands for the mathematics, in this
case of just squaring the Hamiltonian.
So, what actually happens is
superposition of all possible things.
Yeah. And so, that's why the energy of
any individual one need not be
conserved.
Yeah.
And there's all kinds of Don't forget,
there's all sorts of terms in the
energy. In counting up all the energy,
don't forget to count up these
interaction terms. So, the energy isn't
just the sum of the energy of the
particles, but that sort of gets hidden
in this in these pictures.
It uh
That missing energy that's in the
interactions, you might say, allows
the uh the pictures
to violate energy conservation at each
vertex.
But, you know, if you get confused, you
just go back to where it came from. It
came from the Schrödinger equation going
to the second order in small quantities.
And that's what it means.
Now, we're not going to do Feynman
diagrams in their full-blown glory, but
uh this is where they come from, and uh
this is where the um
The rest is uh just uh technology and uh
tricks to calculate thing things with.
But this is the basic physics of it,
yeah.
Um I I was just thinking about the the
the electric field of the electron
there. Mhm. Um Well, this Yeah, good.
This is the electric field of the
electron.
Well, that's what I was going to ask
about. Um cuz it seems to me that at
least
in a literal sense, I mean, it seems
seems like the field the presence of
field at some distance
um isn't literally created by radiation.
Very good.
It's not uh
I
You could say that the propagation of
the the field ahead of the electron
um obeys the same wave equation of
radiation, but
but it's not literally the radiation.
No, it's not literally the radiation,
although if you take a very high energy
electron,
1% of the time, it behaves as if it were
a real electron and a real photon.
That's because photons move at the speed
of light.
these photons are clearly not going to
move at the speed of light. It's got to
go from here to here and the electron is
not moving with the speed of light.
So, literally thinking of these as
photons moving around is not going to
work.
But if the electron itself is moving
with the speed of light
or close to it, very close to it, then
it really does behave as though it were
a um superposition
of an electron and then an electron with
a real photon, with a genuine photon.
thinking of things where the the
electrons are moving rather slowly.
Yeah. And the field is moving very
quickly as a wave ahead of it.
And then Well, this then you're going to
get yourself completely confused trying
to perform a a model for what's going
on.
Well, I'm just saying it's not literally
Right. creating real photons It's not.
to fill the field. Right.
Right. Okay.
Right. Then don't don't try
to create a um mechanical model of
what's going on. It won't work.
Uh
No, no, but there was effects like
self-interference in the two-slit
experiment.
Self-interference of a single single
photon.
Okay? Is that I don't I don't know. You
have to have sort of the the wave of the
wave
version of the photon.
I mean, you know, the the
meets up with a
its own field,
right? Coming through Well, it's that
has nothing to do with this, though.
Well, it's
it was related to my question.
And you have the
Aharonov-Bohm
experiment so that, you know, the field
is
present at
where
you know, it's not really radiation.
Yeah, no, this is not the radiation
field. This is the induction field.
Right. But as I tell you, when the
electron is fast, it can be thought of
as a radiation field.
Can you finish your thought you were
starting to say about the um Lost it.
It's gone. Finish it. You were starting
to say that if you try to create a model
of this, it will fail. Well, you you'll
try to create the you know, your brain
is always trying to create classical
models, classical pictures for things.
Uh
you can get some experience doing some
calculations and after a while you know
how to deal with these diagrams
and you start to give some
literalness to the diagrams, which
really
is not really right.
It's just a mathematical trick to
calculate H squared, H cubed. Basically,
we're calculating E to the IHT
by expanding it out in powers of H.
Right?
E to the IHT is the time development and
that's what we're expanding out here. 1
- I epsilon H - epsilon epsilon squared
over two. This is this two is the two of
um
of the exponential expansion.
What's the next term?
I guess it's plus I epsilon cubed H
cubed over three factorial.
Right?
Now, how do you actually calculate these
the probability of a given scattering?
That of course requires some
some
some technology which we haven't done.
But
Okay. So so somehow and I I imagine
we're not going to be seeing it tonight
or next week.
This mechanism
uh
if you if you
do the right mathematics with this
mechanism and you have an electron here
and electron here,
you can somehow show the Coulomb
attraction as a classical limit
No. of this process. Yes.
But the way you would do it, the
simplest way to do it,
Well, yes, the answer is yes.
Um
But it's not literally that a photon
jumps from one place to another.
No.
That's a little bit too simplistic.
Yeah. Or is the coupling constant
calculated from first principles
No.
Sometimes
sometimes relationships between coupling
constants can be calculated from
symmetry principles,
but um
generally the coupling constants are
basically experimental input.
Disappointing, isn't it?
Yeah.
On the other hand,
think about what happens when there is a
relation between coupling constants that
dictated by the mathematics, some
symmetry principle,
then it relates two otherwise
independent and different reactions.
When that happens and you go in the
laboratory and you discover that the
reactions behave according to the way
the coupling constants, which have been
determined from first principles, tell
you they're supposed to behave,
that's exhilarating. Doesn't happen very
often,
but happens. Does happen. Difference
between an accidental symmetry
Yeah.
Accidental symmetries are accidents and
they usually don't tell you very much.
Gauge symmetries are the ones that tell
you something.
Okay.
Well, I I take back what I said.
Accidental symmetries also tell you
things.
Important things.
We're going to
I had promised to start fermions today
and I'm going to,
but instead of um talking about fermion
fields, which will come to next time,
let's talk about the Dirac equation.
Let's start the Dirac equation today.
From one point of view, the Dirac
equation, first of all, that means we're
entering into relativity theory. We're
using relativity theory.
Thus far,
what we did was to study
non-relativistic
second quantization.
Now, we want to um
move on a little bit
and study the relativistic electron.
We're going to study we're going to
begin with a one-dimensional electron,
an electron only moving in one direction
dimension. The simplest possible theory
of a electron. It's not a realistic
theory. Electrons move in three
dimensions,
but it's the easiest place to get
started. Without having to throw a bunch
of formulas and a bunch of symbols,
we can study the one-dimensional
electron
and learn quite a lot
with without getting spurious complexity
because of the three-dimensionality of
space.
Then we come back to three dimensions. 3
+ 1 three dimensions, right?
Okay. So,
the electron ought to have a Schrödinger
equation.
Particles should have Schrödinger
equations.
On the other hand, it shouldn't be
if we're if we're dealing with
relativity, incidentally, the reason why
uh we deal with relativity when we deal
with electrons is cuz electrons are
pretty light.
They move around and they move around
and of course in an accelerator we can
get them up to essentially the speed of
light,
but I'm thinking now back to the age of
Dirac.
Why would Dirac have bothered using a
relativistic theory other than curiosity
perhaps about how relativistic electrons
work?
And the answer is that in atom, and
particularly in a hydrogen atom,
the electron moves with a with an
appreciable fraction of the speed of
light, about 1% of the speed of light.
So, relativity is an important
correction for the motion of electron.
If you take heavy atoms,
where the inner electrons are closer to
the nucleus, they are really moving and
they can be pretty close to they're not
moving with the speed of light, but they
can be moving with even more appreciable
um
velocities.
So, if you want to get atoms right,
not just
you know, to zeroth order, you want to
get the corrections to atoms right, the
important corrections are relativistic.
So,
now whether Dirac was was motivated by
that fact or he was just motivated by um
curiosity about how to make relativistic
Schrödinger equations, I don't know.
Okay. Um
The relate
We begin in in formulating the idea of a
Schrödinger equation for a particle,
we begin pretty much with a classical
relationship
between energy and momentum.
We start with energy as a function of
momentum.
Now, really we of course we should go
from quantum mechanics to classical
mechanics
because that's the logic, but what we
tend to know about is classical physics
and so we usually go in the other
direction.
And for an ordinary non-relativistic
particle, the energy, which I'll call a
Hamiltonian, or let's call it E. Let's
call it E. But remember, it is the
Hamiltonian.
It's
E equals P squared over 2M.
That's the energy as a function of
momentum and then to go to quantum
mechanics, we replace energy by
Hamiltonian,
which we then replace
by I d by dt.
In other words, the Hamiltonian is a
thing which gives you the time
derivative of the wave function. That's
on the left side, and on the right side
we replace P
by minus I
d by dx.
And that gives us the Schrödinger
equation.
d psi by dt or I d psi by dt
is minus d squared over 2m
second derivative, you know the story.
Schrödinger equation.
Okay, so Dirac said, "Why don't I do the
same thing?
What's the energy as a function of
momentum?" Oy, it's
ugly.
Square root of p squared plus m squared.
Let's write down because we'll need it
later, the relation between energy and
momentum.
E squared
equals
p squared plus m squared. Now, I've set
the speed of light equal to one and I
will do so continuously throughout.
Speed of light is equal to one.
E squared is equal to p squared plus m
squared. From this you can write down
immediately an equation
if you take E to be
I d by dt, then what is E squared?
It's the second derivative with respect
to t. Minus the second derivative with
respect to t.
So, you would write down
minus second derivative with respect to
t squared, that's E
on some phi of x or psi of x, some wave
function.
Equals p squared, that's minus d by dx
squared
psi plus m squared psi.
Or phi, whatever, phi, psi, I don't
know.
Doesn't matter, whatever we call it.
The wave function of the electron. Or
the wave function of something.
Anybody know what the name of this
equation is?
I seem to have uh
Yeah, that's that's right, that's
Yeah, that's right. That's the
Klein-Gordon equation.
And you might say that Dirac, why didn't
he do this?
I don't know why he didn't do this. He
had an argument. His argument was,
"Look, we're supposed to write,
according to the according to my
principles of quantum mechanics, which
are in my textbook,
we're supposed to write I d by dt is
equal to h times psi.
We're not supposed to have to square the
second derivative. I don't want to know
what the E square what H squared is, I
want to know what H is.
That's what I wrote in my book and I'm
going to stick by it."
Okay?
So, he wants an equation
that reads
I
d, let's call it psi.
Now, it's not a field operator, it's
just a wave function for an electron.
by dt
is equal to some H, some operator on
psi.
What kind of an operator?
Well, it's got to have the momentum,
it's got to have the mass.
He could just put here the square root
of p squared plus m squared and then
write, okay, then he could write he
could write the following strange
equation.
is equal to
square root
of p squared, which is minus d by dx
squared
plus m squared
psi.
What on earth does that mean?
What what does the square root of
d by dx squared plus m squared mean? It
doesn't mean very much. Well, it it it
you can you can give it some technical
meaning, but it's pretty horrible.
It's not a nice the square root of a
differential operator like this is not a
nice thing.
So, I think that Dirac just backed away
from it and said, "I don't like that.
I don't like that. I don't have a I
don't have a convincing case against it,
but um but I'm going to start over
again. I'm going to start from the
beginning." And here's what he said.
We'll do it we'll do it in the
one-dimensional case and then we'll come
back to uh
Let's start the one-dimensional case
with a um
with a a massless particle, a particle
with no mass.
An electron that doesn't have a mass.
And we'll put the mass back in and we'll
see how that works.
All right.
So,
here's what you know about a particle
moving along the x-axis
with the speed of light. It's massless,
so it moves with the speed of light.
It's momentum
is equal to its energy.
Strictly speaking, if I put the speed of
light back we go over here.
Energy is equal to c times the momentum.
This is true for a photon.
It's true for any massless particle.
Okay?
This is a massless particle moving to
the right. What about a massless
particle moving to the left,
incidentally?
Yeah, P would be negative in that case.
P would be positive if the particle
moves to the right. If the particle
moves to the left then P is negative,
but clearly the energy should still be
positive. So, we would have to write P
equals minus E. Well, we only get to
write one thing. We don't get to write
We don't get to write both.
So, let's start with P equals E
and content ourselves with studying a
particle moving to the right.
So, we know what this says. We've
actually studied this equation.
This equation, if we now say that
E is equal to the Hamiltonian and
Hamiltonian is I d by dt
it says I
d psi by dt
that's H psi
is equal to P times psi and that's minus
I
d psi by dx.
That's a pretty simple equation.
d psi, what does it say? It says
d psi by dt
plus d psi by dx equals zero.
What kind of What are the solutions of
such an equation?
No?
They're functions of x minus t.
Any function of x minus t will satisfy
this equation.
A function of x minus t is a wave which
is moving along the axis to the right
with
the speed of light. Speed of light now
being chosen to be equal to one.
Any function of x minus t, psi psi
is a function of x minus t.
That means it describes a wave moving to
the right, a rigid
profile.
Profile doesn't change.
But the location of the center of the
wave changes and it moves with the speed
of light.
Okay, this is a fine equation, very
nice.
Um
Two things wrong with it.
Two things and they're unrelated things.
They're unrelated, they're not the same
thing.
The first thing that's wrong with it is
it's got negative energy. What if the
momentum is negative?
We're allowed to have negative momentum.
Momentum is a is a observable which can
be positive or negative.
It's negative
if uh if it's pointing along the minus
x-axis, it's positive if it's along the
plus x-axis.
It's got particles of negative energy
with negative momentum.
This sounds very dangerous. It sounds
like we can
take those
we can just keep filling up the world
with more and more negative energy
particles, lowering the energy, lowering
it, lowering it without bound from
below.
That's a pretty dangerous
situation. We don't want that.
So, first problem with this is it
contains particles of negative energy.
We got to fix that.
The second problem with it is it only
has particles which move to the right.
Okay?
Well, we could imagine a theory of
particles that only move to the right,
but it wouldn't look like certainly
wouldn't look like
garden variety electrons. We don't know
any particles that only move along one
direction.
Uh if it can move to the if it can move
to the right, it can also move to the
left.
Uh so, that's another thing we can try
to fix.
Okay, so here's what Dirac said.
He said
in in effect, in effect, it's not
exactly what he said, but in effect he
said let's
take two species.
This is to get rid of the left-right
story, not the energy story.
To get rid of the left-right story, he
said, "Let's take two species.
Let's call it psi one and psi two.
Two species of electrons, one of which
we'll think of as the species of
electrons which move to the right and
the other we'll think of as the species
of electrons which go to the left. And
let's just write down two separate
equations.
Let's call them
and think of two separate kinds of
particles.
Or
we can say a particle can be one kind or
the other.
If we have only one particle, it could
be the right kind or the left kind.
And so, let's put um a psi one here.
This is the equation for particles which
move to the right.
And what about the equation for
particles to move to the left, which
we'll call psi two?
That's the equation
psi
two by dt
minus
d psi two by dx
is equal to zero.
Now, in quantum mechanics, of course,
if you can have a particle of type one
and a particle of type two, you can have
a linear superposition of them.
So, you can have particles which have a
probability a half, for example, of
moving to the left and a half moving to
the right. But this is These are the um
These are the wave functions of the two
kinds of particles.
So, Dirac next said, "Look,
it looks to me like what we're talking
about is a particle with a degree of
freedom,
an extra degree of freedom, not just x,
not just the coordinate position or
equivalently the momentum. You can trade
one for the other.
But it looks like it has a discrete
thing,
a plus oneness or a minus oneness, sort
of like a spin. It's not a spin,
but sort of like a spin. It can either
be up or it can be down.
Up in this case means traveling to the
right, down means traveling to the left.
So, he understood a little bit about
matrices and so forth. And he said,
"Look, let's write this in matrix form.
Let's introduce observables
which tell you whether you're one or
two.
And that means that what we want to do
is take our psi's and think of them as a
column vector, psi one and psi two.
Put them together
like so.
This is the amplitude that the particle
is right moving. This is the amplitude
that the particle is left moving.
And let's introduce matrices.
In particular, let's introduce a matrix
whose eigenvectors
are one or two. In other words,
one or two.
Here's a matrix
which
the eigenvectors
are one with eigenvalue one
and minus one with eigenvalue two. So,
here is an observable
which distinguishes
the two kinds of particles.
The up
Well, it's not up or down, but it's
moving to the right or it's moving to
the left.
And we'll just give this matrix a name.
Now, if it was spin,
and it's the observable, it is the
observable, the matrix observable or the
or the operator, the linear operator,
which distinguishes between the two
kinds of particles.
Okay? It's very much like a spin being
up or a spin being down, except that
it's not spin.
Okay, this matrix has a name.
Anybody know what its name is? I forget.
No, I don't.
It's
It is sigma three. It's a Pauli matrix,
but it's a Pauli matrix in the context
where we're thinking about spin, and
spin has to do with angular momentum.
It's just not that here.
All right?
Uh it's just a different thing.
Uh
Dirac called it alpha.
He called it alpha, so let's call it
alpha. And it's exactly that matrix.
And then he wrote What I'm saying he did
this, he actually didn't do this. He
plunged right in and did it in three
dimensions.
But
uh
I don't know, maybe for all I know,
maybe he did do this, but uh
It might make a certain a different kind
of sense in three dimensions.
When you have the direction, a vector
type direction.
Yeah.
Right, it does it does.
But if you were doing it in one
dimension, which is the easy baby way to
get started, and it's not so baby, it's
it's it's correct. Uh you would write
that h instead of the Hamiltonian,
instead of
e is the Hamiltonian, but now but now
we're thinking of it as a Hamiltonian,
not just a number.
The Hamiltonian
is
p if the particle is moving to the right
and minus p if the particle
The two kinds of particles, one move to
the right, the other goes. So, it's p if
it's a right mover and minus p if it's a
left mover.
But the right movers and the left movers
are distinguished by alpha.
So, we can summarize it by just writing
h equals alpha p.
If alpha is plus one, it's a right
mover. If alpha is minus one, it's a
left mover.
So, he puts together into a single
structure
a particle with a degree of freedom,
which is its position, and another
degree of freedom with with it which is
its alpha.
Put it together and says h is equal to
alpha p.
This now becomes an equation. You can
write it in a number of ways. Here is
one way of writing it.
But we can also write it
as i
d by dt
of
psi one psi two,
a two-component column vector,
is equal
to alpha, which is the matrix 1 - 1 0 0,
times minus i
d psi by dx.
Let's put the minus i over here.
Or
You got psi one and psi two. Hm?
Yeah, I'm sorry.
d by dx, good.
d by dx
of psi one psi two.
Or we can just condense it. We don't
need all of this stuff. We can just
write i d psi by dt
is equal to minus i alpha d psi by dx.
But remember that psi is this
two-component column vector. They're all
the same thing.
Keep in mind that uh and
since alpha has both positive and
negative eigenvalue, this describes both
right moving and left moving waves.
Okay, so by the trick of introducing uh
the Dirac matrix alpha
and a two-component structure for the uh
for the wave function, we now have cured
the problem of the one-way uh the
one-way street. It's now a two-way
street.
And electrons
an electron can go either to the left or
the right.
I said there were two things wrong.
Uh
The first I said was the negative
energy. We still have that. The second
was the one-wayness. I forgot a third
one.
So far, the electron has no mass.
This is something moving with the speed
of light.
Okay?
This is not what we want. We want an
electron which moves with less than the
speed of light. In other words, we want
an electron with a mass.
Okay? I think I could have done this.
It took the genius of Dirac to make the
next step.
He said Here's what he said.
Well, let's
He said, "Let's just add a term to the
Hamiltonian and see if we can get it to
come out to be a mass."
I'm going to add something here.
It ought to be proportional to the mass.
m equals, of course, means mc squared
strictly. It's the energy of a particle
at rest when it has no momentum.
So, we want something to account for the
energy of a particle when it has no
momentum.
But since all of these equations now are
acting on these two-component columns,
in general, this thing has to be a
matrix. It's got to be something which
can act It could be the unit matrix for
all I know, but let's not prejudice it.
Let's add something here proportional to
the mass.
And let's introduce another matrix and
let's call it beta.
Okay.
Now, here I have a feeling I probably
would not have caught this. Dirac did.
And uh
And moreover, caught it in three
dimensions, which is a little bit
harder, but not much.
Okay. So,
this is some operator. It's a genuine
operator. p is the momentum operator.
Alpha is the alpha operator. Beta is
some operator
which has only to do with the um with
the two-componentness.
It doesn't have to do with x. It doesn't
have to do with p. It just acts on the
two-component
uh spinners. We'll call them spinners
for what they are.
And here's what he said. He said, "Look,
here's what I know. I know that in a
relativistic theory,
the energy squared, which is the
Hamiltonian squared,
should equal p squared plus m squared.
Let's insist on this.
Let's insist on this. Let's insist that
when I square this
when I square H that I get P squared
plus M squared. So, let's see what that
says.
All right. So, that says
H squared which is E squared
should equal alpha P plus beta M
times
alpha P plus beta M.
Okay. First of all, I'm going to get a P
squared term. It's going to be alpha
squared Oh, incidentally, alpha commutes
with P. It acts in a different tensor
product Hilbert space. We don't have to
worry about commutation between alphas
and Ps.
Okay. The first term is alpha squared P
squared.
That looks good. We want to get P
squared. We got alpha squared P squared.
It's easy to deal with. Let's just make
Let's just insist that alpha squared be
one.
But wait a minute. We already know what
alpha is.
Alpha is this matrix over here.
Its square is one.
So, we're in good shape with the P
squared term.
That's good.
If we use the fact that we know what
alpha is
then this is just P squared.
How about the M squared term? There's
another term which is beta squared M
squared.
Well, I don't know what beta is yet. I
haven't decided what beta is yet.
But what do I know? I know that beta
squared should be one.
So, let's write down what we know.
Alpha squared equals one.
That's good. We have that already.
Beta squared equals one. There's lots of
matrices around whose square is equal to
one, so not to worry. Any one of the
Pauli matrices its square is equal to
one. One means identity matrix, right?
One means the identity matrix, yes. Any
of the Pauli matrices its square is
equal to one. The identity matrix itself
its square is equal to one.
Okay. So, we've taken care of that. But
now
this is P squared plus M squared.
But then we have an extra term.
And the extra term is alpha beta.
It's a product of P with M.
And it's got one term which has alpha
beta and another term which has beta
alpha.
So, it has alpha beta plus beta alpha
times PM.
We don't want that term.
That term is something we don't want.
Hm? So, they should anti-commute. So,
they should anti-commute. So, we want
that alpha beta
plus beta alpha
is equal to zero.
And once we do that, then we have our
cake and eat it. We first of all have an
equation
of this very simple kind that that Dirac
like so much, namely
where is it? H on psi equals I psi dt
for one thing. And we also have that E
squared equals P squared plus M squared.
All we have to do is find a matrix
which anti-commutes. That means when you
change the order the sign changes, which
anti-commutes with alpha.
Now, I
uh Pauli had already invented his
matrices.
And Dirac, had he done things this way,
would have instantly recognized that
this happens to be one of the Pauli
matrices.
And he also would have known that any
pair of the Pauli matrices anti-commute.
So, he could simply take for beta any
other of the
Pauli matrices. In practice, he took
those equations that you wrote down
and just said, well, that
he already knows the Pauli matrices do
that.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
He did have Pauli to back him up on
this. I mean, Pauli had already
done
lots of work with these.
Hm? He just used unknowns He did.
Yeah, he did.
But then he said, let's find some
matrices which do this. All right. So,
in this case
in this case, um
we can we have a choice about beta.
But let's let's resolve that
ambiguity. It's not a real genuine
ambiguity. It It's It's a convention.
But here's in the second matrix. Beta,
this is alpha, and this is beta.
Namely 0 1 1 0.
You can go home and check
that alpha times beta is minus beta
times alpha. I'm not going to do it on
the blackboard. It's a straightforward
thing.
They do anti-commute. And so, Dirac now
had his
his um
equation. And let's see what it says.
Let's see what kind of equation he had.
Isn't that Einstein's beta, right?
What's that? It's not Einstein's beta,
right?
It's not what? The relativistic beta.
No, no. It's a matrix. It's a It's Pauli
matrix. No, no. It's not definitely not
that. We just don't have enough letters.
Yeah.
I'm following Dirac's notation.
Alpha and beta are called Dirac
matrices.
In this case, they're 2 by 2 matrices.
Uh
we'll find out probably next week that
you can't do it with 2 by 2 matrices in
three dimensions, but but we'll do
something else.
Okay. So, let's see what this says.
This says Where was our equation? It
says I
d psi dt where psi is a two-component
spinner
is equal to alpha
P
times psi plus beta M
times psi.
Where M is the mass.
Okay. Let's write it out.
As a two-component equation, this is I
and in the first slot here we would
write d psi by dt.
So, well, let's let's let's write it.
I d by dt
psi one psi two.
And this stands for a column made out of
I d psi one dt and I d psi two dt.
Then we have alpha. And alpha
is 1 -1
0 0
times P. But P is minus I d by dx.
So, we have a minus I equals minus I
d by dx
of psi one psi two.
Now, so far we're just rewriting the two
equations here.
Just rewriting these two equations,
separate equations for psi one and psi
two. And the reason they're separate is
because this matrix is diagonal. It does
not mix psi one with psi two.
But then we have beta. And so, let's add
plus beta. And beta is
1 1 0 0.
We have to multiply it by M. So, let's
put the M right in here, M right in
here.
Psi one psi two.
If we write out this term
we'll find that the upper because the
psi one is off diagonal. Sorry, because
this because the beta is off diagonal.
Uh
what does this do?
It switches psi one and psi two.
So, this term this term here just
becomes
M
psi two psi one.
So, let's come back to this equation
over here. What it does, I'll never get
the I in the right place. So, yeah,
let's put the I in the right place. I
I
minus I
equals and now it looks like this one is
M psi two and the other one is M psi
one.
So, you see, once you introduce the mass
term
the two components are not independent
anymore. They interact with each other.
The equation couples one to the other.
And what is the What does that coupling
do?
It gives the particle a mass.
And if you work out how it moves, it
moves slower than the speed of light. It
moves as if it were a particle
with E squared equals P squared plus M
squared. In other words, a relativistic
particle of finite mass.
This is what Dirac did
to get rid of the left-right
nonsense and at the same time to get a
mass. Now, I suspect he knew something
else.
That that
that the mass was connected with the
left-rightness.
If you have a
a particle which is massless
it's consistent to just think that it
can only go along the right along in in
one dimension. That it only goes in one
direction.
And the reason is because any Lorentz
transformation of a particle moving to
the right is still a particle moving to
the right if it's moving with the speed
of light.
A Lorentz transformation will not take a
particle moving to the right with a
speed of light and convert it to a
particle moving to the left with the
speed of light.
Okay? So, particles which move with the
speed of light
the left ones and the right ones don't
talk to each other through Lorentz
transformations.
If a particle has a mass, you can bring
it to rest.
Or you can Yeah, you can you can maybe
not bring it to rest, but you can bring
it to some finite momentum along the x a
finite velocity along the x-axis.
So, it's moving with half the speed of
light this way,
and then you get on your horse and run
with 3/4 of the speed of light.
It is now moving in the opposite
direction. So, it's just not possible to
have a massive particle which only moves
to the right. So, Dirac knew
I I
again, I I imagine he knew that the
left-to-rightness was coupled together
with the mass issue.
And that by fixing the left-to-right
issue,
he could potentially create a mass for
the electron. Yeah. Is this in some
sense a chiral oscillation? What's that?
Is this in some sense related to chiral
oscillation?
Um
the left-to-rightness is called the
chirality
in this case. It means handedness.
Uh in this case In this case, the two
swapping of two and one is what I think
of.
Yeah, um no, in this case No, in this
case, the handedness is just the alpha
matrix over here. It's not a swap, but
uh it's the mass term which is the swap.
Yeah, I was just talking about the whole
the whole equation. Is there Is there a
chiral oscillation built into that?
Yeah.
The mass term is the chiral oscillation.
Yeah. Yeah. Oh, absolutely.
Yeah.
Mhm.
What Why should a fermion equation come
from the square root of a boson
equation?
No, no, no, no. This has nothing to do
with fermions or bosons. E² = P² + M²
for any particle for any relativistic
system.
Yeah, as long as it's not massless.
E² is equal to P² + M². That has nothing
particular to do with whether it's a um
Every particle satisfies that.
Right?
So,
it's true you can sort of think of the
Dirac equation as a kind of square root
of the Klein-Gordon equation, but I
don't think that's particularly helpful.
All right. So, the last thing we have to
do
is get straight
E minus M D plus M factorization, which
is sort of left movers, right movers.
Mhm.
All right. So, we have two things to do
with the Dirac equation.
One is to understand how to get rid of
the negative energies. This is not
gotten rid of the negative energies.
Now, we have negative energy right
movers and negative energy left movers.
We made it worse.
And the other is to get the
three-dimensional space.
But that's easy.
Just Yeah.
You just pointed back and you said the
Dirac equation just this pair of
equations constitute the Dirac equation.
For the one-dimensional case.
Yeah. Yeah, this is a really long
version of the Dirac equation. Mhm.
The usual equation.
No.
The Dirac equation would be written this
way.
I d psi by dt
is equal to minus or Well, sorry. It's
equal to Yeah.
minus I alpha
d psi by dx
plus beta m psi.
That would be the Dirac equation written
in uh
one form.
You can also
write it another way, which is also
these days more familiar.
You multiply both sides of the equation
by beta.
And you write
I
Ah, let's come to it next time.
It's enough for tonight. It's enough for
tonight.
There's a more symmetric way to write
it, which is pretty and the standard way
to write it, but it doesn't add anything
at this point.
Good.
Okay, we're finished.
For more, please visit us at
stanford.edu.